Heraklion, Crete, Greece Open to relocation ammarkov@gmail.com

# Ammar Qammaz

Software / Research / Computer Vision / Robotics / Al

github.com/AmmarkoV/ linkedin.com/ammarkov/

13+ years of tracked experience in C / C++, 10+ years working on research projects specializing on Computer Vision as member of the Computer Vision and Robotics Laboratory of FORTH, the largest research institute in Greece. Areas of expertise: Computer Vision, Artificial Neural Networks, 3D human perception and pose estimation, Real-Time Computing, Robotics, HCI. Impact: Among the top most active Github developers in Greece, Author of MocapNET one of the few 3D total Human Pose estimation methods in the world, 409+ citations in top-tier conferences including CVPR, ICPR, BMVC, ICCVW, in charge of the human perception stack of EU FP7 Hobbit robot, a.k.a. first robot trials in houses of elderly people in human history, GNU/Linux enthusiast, various FOSS contributions.

#### **PROJECTS**

Magician, iMmersive leArninG, ImperfeCtion detectIon repAir human-robot interactioN (EU Grant no.101120731)

2024 — Present

Technical lead, providing a computer vision neural network based solution for defect repair in industrial assembly lines.

Greece 4.0, Scene understanding based on visual information (KA 11413, No. 90213)

2024 — Present

• Technical lead, providing a distributed computer vision neural network pose estimation and scene understanding for industrial use.

CardioSCOPE, Empowering scientists for the "omics" era (MSCA SE project funded by EU Grant no.101086397)

2023 - 2024

· Trained in High-performance liquid chromatography and Liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry in B.S.N. srl

AUTO-MNET, BonsApps (EU H2020 Grant no.101015848) AI Talent grant (Winner No. Bons 10C 20)

2022 - 2023

• Technical lead, providing an embedded 3D real-time driver body pose estimation framework for cars to ensure safe driving.

I.C.HUMANS, HFRI (ΕΛΙΔΕΚ Proj. No. 91)

2021 - 2022

• Unobtrusive capturing of human motion articulation and semantics.

Mingei, EU H2020 grant no. 822336

2018 - 2020

• 3D pose estimation from RGB videos of experts performing various historically important procedures for cultural preservation

Co4Robots, EU H2020-ICT-2016-1-73186

2017 - 2019

· Preparing deliverables, experiments on real-time RGB human perception on the ROS platform

## Hobbit The Mutual Care Robot, EU FP7-ICT-288146

2013 - 2015

In charge of implementing the RGBD human perception stack of the Robot, emergency user fall detection, system design/tuning, web interface using my embedded AmmarServer, review meeting demos and on-site support on live trials.

#### Robohow.cog, EU FP7-ICT-288533

2013 - 2015

Integration of FORTH 3D Hand Pose estimation and 3D Object Tracking framework with ROS and the PR2 robot, Work on force sensing based on vision (See CVPR '15 Publication), 3D tracking performance improvements (See BMVC '15 Publication).

## **GuarddoG Robot Project, BSc Thesis**

2008 - 2012

• Software and hardware for a small autonomous wheeled robot for domestic security and surveillance designed from scratch.

## **EXPERIENCE**

#### PhD Graduate Research Assistant

Jan 2019 — Apr 2024

Computer Vision and Robotics Lab, Institute of Computer Science, Foundation of Research and Technology

Heraklion

- Involvement in I.C.HUMANS, SustAGE, Mingei Projects and BonsAPPs 1st Support program.
- Created MocapNET and Hierarchical Coordinate Descent algorithm for real-time 3D body and hand pose estimation from RGB.

## **MSc Graduate Research Assistant**

Jan 2015 — Jan 2019

Computer Vision and Robotics Lab, Institute of Computer Science, Foundation of Research and Technology

Heraklion

- Involvement in Co4Robots, RAMCIP and RAPID Projects
- 3D Human pose estimation from RGBD video using a 3D reconstruction of the subject. 3D Hand Tracking and Gesture recognition.

# **Software Research Engineer**

Jan 2013 — Jan 2015

Computer Vision and Robotics Lab, Institute of Computer Science, Foundation of Research and Technology

Heraklion

- Involvement in Hobbit, Robohow.cog Projects
- Model based 3D Hand and Object Pose Estimation from RGBD, developed RGBDAcquisition a framework for 3D data acquisition.

# **Communication systems operator**

Nov 2010 — Aug 2011

Hellenic Army

 Served as a communication systems operator on the HNDGS-NATO headquarters handling classified signals and state secrets. Page 1 / 2

Freelancer Oct 2005 — Nov 2010

- Developed, hosted and maintained e-commerce platforms for car dealerships, jewellery stores, and small businesses.
- Shareware and freeware games, utilities, database software for medical clinics and dentists, still being used today on windows PCs.

#### **EDUCATION**

Frameworks

**Doctor of Philosophy, Computational and Cognitive Vision and Robotics,** University of Crete **Master of Science, Computational and Cognitive Vision and Robotics,** University of Crete, GPA: 8.86/10.00 **Bachelor of Science, Computer Science,** Athens University of Business and Economics, GPA: 6.51/10.00

Jan 2019 — Apr 2024 Oct 2015 — Nov 2018

### Sep 2004 — Sep 2012

#### TECHNICAL SKILLS

**Research Interests** 

Programming Languages Platforms

 ${\sf C,C++,Python,Shell\,scripting} ({\sf BASH,Csh,Perl}), {\sf Java,PHP,SQL,Matlab/Octave,FreePascal}$ 

GNU/Linux, Android, Windows, Embedded (ATMEL, AVR, ESP, Arduino)

OpenCV, OpenGL, GLSL, CUDA, Tensorflow, Keras, NumPy, PThreads, ROS, PCL, Git, WxWidgets Computer Vision, Machine Learning, Artificial Intelligence, Robotics, HCI, Embedded Computing

# SELECTED PUBLICATIONS, FULL PUBLICATION LIST AVAILABLE @ HTTP://AMMAR.GR/PUBLICATIONS/

- 1. Panagou, S. et al. Complexity based investigation in collaborative assembly scenarios via non intrusive techniques. Procedia Computer Science, 4th International Conference on Industry 4.0 and Smart Manufacturing (ISM 2022) 217, 478–485 (2023).
- 2. Qammaz, A. & Argyros, A. A Unified Approach for Occlusion Tolerant 3D Facial Pose Capture and Gaze Estimation using MocapNETs in International Conference on Computer Vision Workshops (AMFG 2023 ICCVW 2023) (IEEE, Paris, 2023).
- 3. Qammaz, A. & Argyros, A. Compacting MocapNET-based 3D Human Pose Estimation via Dimensionality Reduction in International Conference on Pervasive Technologies Related to Assistive Environments (PETRA 2023) (ACM, Greece, 2023).
- 4. Qammaz, A. & Argyros, A. Towards Holistic Real-time Human 3D Pose Estimation using MocapNETs in British Machine Vision Conference (BMVC 2021) (BMVA, Nov. 2021).
- 5. Qammaz, A. & Argyros, A. Occlusion-tolerant and personalized 3D human pose estimation in RGB images in 2020 25th International Conference on Pattern Recognition (ICPR) (2021), 6904–6911.
- 6. Bajones, M. et al. Results of field trials with a Mobile service robot for older adults in 16 private households. ACM Transactions on Human-Robot Interaction (THRI) 9, 1–27 (2019).
- 7. Qammaz, A. & Argyros, A. A. MocapNET: Ensemble of SNN Encoders for 3D Human Pose Estimation in RGB Images. BMVC 2019.
- 8. Bajones, M. et al. Hobbit: providing fall detection and prevention for the elderly in the real world. Journal of Robotics (2018).
- 9. Qammaz, A., Michel, D. & Argyros, A. A hybrid method for 3d pose estimation of personalized human body models in 2018 IEEE Winter Conference on Applications of Computer Vision (WACV) (2018), 456–465.
- 10. Qammaz, A., Kyriazis, N. & Argyros, A. Boosting the Performance of Model-based 3D Tracking by Employing Low Level Motion Cues. in BMVC (2015), 144–1.
- 11. Pham, T.-H. et al. Towards force sensing from vision: Observing hand-object interactions to infer manipulation forces in Proceedings of the IEEE conference on computer vision and pattern recognition (CVPR) (2015), 2810–2819.

## **AWARDS & HONORS**

- 2003 Chosen for International Olympiad of Informatics 2004 Greek team after national programming contest
- 2008 Robotics, best of Show Award for GuarddoG project in the Athens Digital Week event
- 2021 Recipient of the "Maria Michail Manasaki" Bequest Fellowship for the work carried out during the first year of my PhD
- 2022 PhD Scholarship to participate in the ARCHIMEDES Greek ML/AI Summer School after national selection.
- 2022 PhD work on MocapNET awarded a BonsApps (EU H2020 no.101015848) Al Talent grant (Winner No. Bons\_1OC\_20)

## NATIONALITY, LANGUAGES, OTHER INFORMATION & INTERESTS

European/Greek Nationality, Native Greek speaker. English FCE, CPE Cambridge diplomas. INTJ Myers-Briggs personality type, O+ blood type. I enjoy tweaking my custom built Quadcopter, maintaining my open source repositories, gaming, amateur photography, sailing, reading books, good music, watching documentaries, latin dance and traveling.

## LINKS

Google Scholar: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=sDOdhtwAAAAJ, Github: https://github.com/AmmarkoV/, YouTube: http://www.youtube.com/user/ammarkov, HackerRank: https://www.hackerrank.com/ammarkov, Linked-In: https://www.linkedin.com/in/ammarkov, Instagram: https://www.instagram.com/ammarkov1/, Spotify: Ammar Qammaz Page 2 / 2

ly